[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
excited for this one um so welcome to
the stoa
the stoa is a place for us to cohere and
dialogue about what matters most at the
knife's edge of this moment
and it's where all the cool kids come to
sense make what
uh what is happening right now uh in our
world and i'm peter limberg the steward
of the stoa
so for those of you who've been here a
while we know the stoa had
uh featured sense makers such as benita
roy's
psychotechnology playground samuel
burgess live players and uh patrick ryan
stark stoa
and now that we're growing we're
launching a sense maker in residence
series
and these will be four sessions that
happened for the duration of a month
uh so for example we have zach stein
coming in doing uh
one on metapolita meta psychology uh
dave snowden's doing naturalizing
sense making and today uh the first
session of this
series new series called network
tribalism
features john robb so to introduce john
he's a military analyst entrepreneur and
author of a book
brave new world and he releases
something called the global guerrillas
report
which is a report that covers the
intersection of war politics and
technology
with the goal of providing frameworks
needed to make sense of our relentlessly
chaotic world
and how the series is going to work and
how today's
going to work john is going to kind of
share his thoughts on uh
network tribalism and we're going to
have a conversation a collective
conversation
i will warm up some questions and then
if you have a question
put it in the chat box and then i'll
call
uh you to unmute yourself and ask john
your question this will go on youtube so
if you want to
read your question on your behalf uh let
me know this will be an hour and we'll
have a kind of a sense making uh
session 30 minute optional sense making
session afterwards
so that being said uh i will allow john
to unmute himself
and uh john maybe you can just kick
start us off uh by adding anything else
and then
jumping right into it hi everyone um
thanks for coming
um what i'd like to do is just kind of
go over some of the basics of network
tribalism and
what's driving it and how i stumbled
into it
you know one of the best ways of making
sense of what we're going through right
now is to
frame it within the context of network
tribalism and
it's a network tribe as a cohesive
social structure
that uh sprung up online and it
uh is driving our politics it's driving
our social response
it's driving much of the seeming chaos
around us
um i came into the subject
oh whoa back in 2003 2004 when i started
the global
global gorillaz blog you know what i saw
in iraq
with the counter insurgency wasn't
matching the analysis
the traditional analysis on on how
counter
how insurgencies operate
and um what i saw was a an insurgency
operated
very much like a lot of what i saw
online
with open source uh software development
and online behaviors and
that led to a long
process of analysis that eventually
resulted in the book a breakdown war
in 2007 and
what i described then is an open source
insurgency um
an insurgency that wasn't made up of a
single group
that mirrored the nation state in terms
of how
it organized itself with the political
wing and economic wing et cetera
this insurgency was made up of
dozens of different groups in the case
of iraq it was 70 different groups and
they all
seemed to be able to work together in
order to
fight the united states and the iraqi
government
and they uh did this using an open
source dynamic
um it made it really tough to
eliminate so when the counter insurgency
forces
you know found a low-level member of a
group
typically that would result in flipping
them and then going up the chain of
command up the pyramid
until you hit the planting cell and then
you'd wipe them out and the whole thing
would collapse
in this case they'd go up a level maybe
two and the
group would evaporate could be gone that
was the extent of
the group's depth um and
there were 69 other groups to take their
place and then
another group would emerge almost
instantaneously
and the way they operated together was
through uh
kind of an open source innovation
tinkering approach
uh instead of a master strategy or
master plan coming down from on high
they tinkered at the low levels and and
tried things out and whatever stuck
against the wall you know you throw
things against the wall whatever sticks
works and then every if that works uh
everybody copies it
and they implement it and the
communications mechanism was
something i identified as a stigma g out
of uh
insects and and
like ants and bees is that when
something worked
it was like a chemical trail being left
for others to follow and they used the
press
to share that information so if an
attack was successful
in terms of the target in terms of the
technique that would be covered by the
press and the
and the press would then be the chemical
trail
for others to follow and and replicate
um
open source insurgencies became open
source protests during the
uh arab spring um they were
big enough to topple you know
governments
in egypt and tunisia um
eventually in egypt and and led to the
civil war in
syria uh open source protests don't have
a
cohesive leadership they you know many
times they were saying that either they
just started
online using a facebook message and once
i got going
they grew very very rapidly and they
were impossible to shut down um
and uh most recently in the states we
saw them in the uh the election
uh in in 2016.
uh just before that we had occupy and we
had the tea party movement both open
source movements
um mostly in reaction to the 2008
financial crisis
uh and that led to uh something a little
bit more
formal uh you know an open source
insurgency that that took over the
republican party
and used trump as a weapon to take over
the white house um
so uh that kind of set us up into the
current situation
i approached the whole thing as a kind
of a breakdown of the
you know my way into this was uh through
looking at this as a
breakdown of the nation state kind of a
post-westphalian lens
uh that came out of the the warfare
space you know martin van griveld
and bill lind and others have been
writing about this
um the rise of fourth generation warfare
this idea that because
large-scale conventional war wasn't
possible on a north
due to nuclear weapons uh the
scale of the conflict had dropped it was
being fought at
at a very low level at the gorilla level
at the
[Music]
unconventional level and that as we
globalized the nation state broke down
and
that because the nation state broke down
um they weren't able to deliver the
political goods and that
groups would arise within the nation
state
and across nation states that would
challenge it for
dominance and they would use these
unconventional
methods to to take it on
so you know open source insurgencies fit
within that framework for me it was my
way in is
it it proved that it was capable of
taking down
states directly through external force
uh taking down even a governor in puerto
rico
lost to an open source protest
and then also taking over the government
of the united states through through an
election process
and then as i got into the topic and i
started the global uh
rulers report i started finding other
threads in
um two other ones uh in particular uh
one was uh the mcluhan perspective is
that
that social technology kind of the
social technology i helped build back in
2001 that became social networking
uh had rewired our brands
and um we think differently than we used
to
uh very similar to what happened back in
with the printing press when the
printing press hit
it rewired us uh it made
for instance in in terms of religion it
made bibles accessible
i mean even priests and in the 1500s
didn't have a full bible
i mean they had excerpts and they only
read
tiny portions of it it was all uh
largely taught by uh through an oral
tradition
so um that rewiring that
that that went on in with the printing
press was occurring now
with us and online and it was changing
the way we were thinking and because it
was changing the way we were thinking
it would change the way we organized
socially
as kind of an after effect and some of
the ways it changed us
is that we started to think it less as a
kind of you read something in its
entirety
uh and you know in isolation
as an individual inform your opinions
through that reading
the kind of long-form approach to the
kind of short
staccato rhythm of lots and lots of
information
too much information the process is
flowing over you and what you do
is you just pick the pieces out of that
flow
that makes sense and they you can fit
into a pattern
that you are curating um that
pattern making that pattern matching is
constant now i mean we are constantly
pattern matching
we can't handle the flow of information
that's coming over us
and the social consequences of that is
that
pattern matching turns into kind of a
pattern curation it becomes a shared
pattern
that millions of people are are curating
and that
forms the basis of tribalism
um a third one is they came out of the
uh david roenfeld's
uh timid analysis uh tribes institutions
markets networks
uh he's posited that uh
we are on the verge of a new social
decision making system
which is a kind of a positive way to
look at it
that this network piece could become a
something to rival the existing
decision-making systems that got us out
of the the middle ages things like
tribes
tribes became nationalism uh
institutions you know
basic bureaucracy became the the
powerhouse behind science behind
technology behind corporate structures
behind government
and that markets stitched it all
together graded information finding you
know graded
allocation of resources those three
started off very rough and they were
refined over time to be
largely beneficial because we're on a
on a macro level we're certainly a hell
of a lot better off now than we were 500
years ago
um so uh
what do networks add and and the problem
with the new
social decision making system is that it
uh
it's really rough and it can be abused
and it could be
emerging malformed and cause all sorts
of problems um
i mean think of the kind of the worst
case scenario with bureaucracy
bureaucracy is great
at mobilizing resources and getting
things done at scale
but it doesn't have any moral compass
it's just a set of procedures that work
in a in a hierarchy with with the
many many people following uh wrote
descript job descriptions and and and
orders that come down from on high
um and the abuse of that ended up in say
concentration camps or ended up in the
totalitarianism of communism where you
had a single bureaucracy
running everything um
and you know the same thing would be
with markets i mean early markets were
definitely very
brutal in terms of how unequal the
income distribution
and the wealth distribution
was so you'd starve even though the
market was free
um so network decision making what is
that
well we got a little taste of it and i'm
trying to
you know piece it together as i'm going
along but it was this
it operates differently than the other
three
um it's to a certain extent more
powerful than the other three
uh it works on a dynamic between
consensus and descent
a functional network decision making
system consensus is that we all agree
to do something and if it's working
correctly that
that something is very narrow and it's
situation specific and it lasts
for a short period of time until that
task is done or to that
goal is achieved um we got that
initially with
the coven response uh
we all pretty much agreed that we wanted
to stop it from taking root in the
united states
um and that we took a lot of action as
individuals that slowed it down we
pretty much used that network consensus
to shut down the country to
move to work from home to uh reorganize
ourselves in ways that
that muted the response well before the
the the state the bureaucracy actually
made the decision to do anything and
that was all done with an absence of
information even though the fda
cdc screwed up and didn't get any tests
produced i mean we had no feedback loop
through all of february and into late
march
uh because we did at beginning march we
only had 300 tests
a day in a nation of 330 million because
of that screw-up
and even that didn't stop the network
from responding effectively
not effective enough but it shows the
power of the system
and the descent and the other part is
the descent the dynamic
the set will actually constantly pick
away at the consensus and make sure that
it doesn't
persist beyond its shelf life you know
uh or that doesn't
exceed its reach and we've seen that
with the covered response
as the
consensus flailed at actually solving
the problem the descent grew and grew
and grew and it continues to grow
um the dissent prevents the consensus
from locking things in
and that you know that's a functional
decision-making system and refinement
over time
maybe over decades maybe over a century
we could get that thing working in
in a way that actually yields some
benefit i mean just the way that we
combine markets with bureaucracy that we
use the markup system to
to elect leaders that ran bureaucracies
through you know elections
that kind of combination that kind of
cross fertilization could be beneficial
the problem is is that um
when it is dysfunctional that the
consensus
can lock everything in it can lock
everything down
into a single cohesive view um
and and it could be so total
and it's using network technologies
using interconnections
um the way we run our economy way we run
our society that
will prevent anything else from
happening
the opposite being true is that the
descent could win and we end up
in just perpetual chaos um
my fear is more the total lockdown
and and if you look internationally you
could say maybe china is more the
consensus consensus-driven
approach they're moving towards a total
lockdown for
in order to make themselves more capable
of handling the expresses of a
globalized environment
um but at a massive reduction in
freedom of movement and innovation and
then the descent
side would be more like russia where
everything is just chaotic constantly
and the only people that benefit is like
the the core of interlocked
uh corrupt companies that are at the
center of things
um network tribes emerge out of this
out of the consensus and
you know what we're seeing now is is a
consensus that
uh through pattern matching has built up
tribes that you know
dominate the conversation they've taken
to the streets and they're
rolling up uh political power
and the fear is that over time
maybe even just a year or two that we
could end up in a consensus lockdown
into a tribal lockdown
because these tribes aren't just a you
know an opinion they
start to become cohesive social units
due to the dynamics of tribalism
tribalism works really really well
online and even mcluhan would say that
we could when we became global villagers
we've re-tribalized we've you know we're
not
global village always was seemed so
hopeful is that we're all together
but it's actually global villagers are
backbiters they're constantly monitoring
each other's behavior they're constantly
in each other's business and they kill
outsiders they kill people who deviate
i mean some of the worst things happen
of course at the tribal level
at the village level when somebody does
not
conform so um that kind of gives you a
background going in and i'm opening up
to any kind of questions that
want to go on from here
great so if you have any questions start
throwing it in the the chat box right
now
um yeah just like uh
just deflect something before i forget
uh david uh ron felt uh
the timid framework he's coming in on
august 26th so talk about his new
thing called whose story wins so that
should be cool um
i'll warm you up with a few questions
and we'll go to the question in the chat
uh is there anything that you would like
to prime
us with this group uh that's here live
or
people that are watching this on the
youtube channel um something that's at
your edge of your thinking ideas that
you would like to stress test
throughout these four weeks at this
series that we have
um at the very edge
well there's a you know a big
debate in my head in terms of how this
conflict rolls out
right and so i'm working through that um
and what that means for the us uh coming
up through the election and after this
election
the election is it's both more important
and less important than many people
think
that this tribal conflict is is actually
the thing that's
dominant underneath the scenes and then
uh i have some thinking that i was
been doing in terms of you know it kind
of reforms or
or tweaks to the system that we could
make that that would give us a path out
and that not only out of this but that
would set in motion
a a a set of changes in a set of uh
uh social dynamics that that would
you know improve our lives over the long
term and that has to do with the
data ownership and thinking in terms of
data ownership and kind of a
creating a version of that online that
that moves your interests forwards but
you can't get that without ownership
and there's a lot of questions about
that maybe that would be the last
session
right and um so the question i had is uh
kind of the current players in this sort
of culture 2.0 or there's kind of
there's just tribal warfare that's
happening
like antifa um black lives matter uh
q anon you have any thoughts on how that
is playing out with the current election
yeah um well the the tribes and this is
interesting um typically in the past
tribalism um was driven forward by a
you know a positive narrative a positive
story
this is why you know a story that says
this is why we are better together
uh this is why you are special this is
why you know
we uh should stick together
and this is all here are all the things
that we've done together in order to
overcome adversity tribes in the online
world
um don't form based on this positive
narrative
they form on based on a pattern
that describes their enemies a pattern
of behavior that
is descriptive of what they oppose
so um that pattern
becomes the basis of fictive kinship
fictive kinship is a way to extend uh
your connection to people beyond uh
actual blood relationship it's the
basis of nationalism it's the basis of
of of
any kind of large-scale group cohesion
and thing is you need that victim
kinship in order to
make things work because without that
fictitionship there's a chance
and and it becomes almost
self-fulfilling
is that um you won't trust or people
won't trust what other people are saying
to them
because they don't think that they are
connected they're not kin
in any even a loose sense that whatever
they say is false
even the most basic fact even the most
basic observation that they have
uh is seen as something malicious and
we're
at that stage now as the nationalism our
former form
of victim kitchen dissolves is weakened
as we punch holes in it we're less
trusting of everybody else
uh we don't even attract we don't even
agree on the basic facts because we
don't trust that the other person
presenting those facts
those observations are being truthful so
um
in the case of online tribes um these
negative patterns
uh are curated by millions of people
and they go out and they find examples
of these every day
and that if they can find a video of it
or or something that has some
kind of empathic content they post it
and then everyone goes i knew it
that's example what this pattern means
or you know this is everywhere
um the big patterns i've seen right now
is
i put those in my most recent reports
you have the anti-racist
the anti-fascists you have on the on the
right tribes you have more the
anti-terrorists
uh the anti-anti-americans which are
basically the
you know anti-traitors right um and
there are a lot of other little minor
tribes that are less effective
below that um so far the left tribes are
stronger
i mean granted they have more of a of a
driver they see trump in the white house
and he poses
they've been cast as an existential
threat and that has driven tribe growth
the right tribes are have been slower to
form um
largely because they you know they have
trump in the white house which serves
kind of as a bullwork as long as he's
kind of like the canary in the coal mine
he's kind of a as long as he's still in
place
the existential threat from what's going
on in portland and other places doesn't
seem as dire
um then once he's removed that could
change and also
trump is not sticking to the the
patterns
he jumps around and that jumping around
means he's not you know helping
the tribes form at all he throws out
things every once in a while they're
tribal specific and
like for instance when he sent the the
security forces security detail to
portland
that was to try to get this kind of
anti-terrorist
you know anti-anarchist kind of
tribal movement going it wasn't really
that effective because people didn't see
them as
existential threats to the degree
necessary to get that
rolling um but there may be some
mechanisms that he may be able to play
to do that but i in general he's he's
not
helping the tribalization on the right
so um
yeah i could keep on going you want to
switch a question or
yeah um okay i'll just sneak in one
follow-up question because it was really
interesting
uh because i agree that the my read on
the
culture 2.0 is that people on the right
the tribes on the right are more
fragmented
than the tribes on the on the left which
makes them less i guess potent or
powerful
um with one exception that seems to be
rising is the q anon
tribe um could you speak a little bit
on that i think q anon for the most part
is i mean they're driven by pattern
matching right
and they uh uh a pattern of conspiracy
that's arrayed against them
right and that they are a malformed
tribe of the right largely but they can
cross uh
it's because the right tribalism hasn't
really
flourished hasn't really taken off
uh and people would say oh yeah well
trump's in office but
it's really he's he's not leading a
tribe per se he led an insurgency the
open source insurgency to get
into power he he's more of a weapon they
placed in power to kind of
kind of a grenade that constantly goes
off and disrupts things
but he's not a tribal leader
in that regard so q anon is is
you know formed out of itself i think
would be eaten up
once the the tribes on the right start
to form
it'll just be absorbed right in it'll
disappear
right now it is it's just out there and
it's you know it shows the power of
pattern matching and how
you know identifying with it and
constantly adding to it and
growing a pattern can actually be
powerful it makes helps people make
sense it helps people
deal with the overload of information
and the chaos around them
cool let's let's switch to some uh
questions in the chat uh benita
roy you have a question
if you can unmute yourself um yeah
um so i actually have two questions that
kind of like wrapped in one question
so um maybe you can help me suss it out
and that is
uh what kind of recommendations can you
make or that people are making to
change the way the algorithms on social
media
either contribute to a functional
network
uh kind of decision making
or uh detract or obstruct that i mean
um it seems to me that we're studying
social media that has doesn't it's not
incentivized to have a functional
network intelligence right and yet still
you're seeing
some of these some of these effects so
how consciously could we
uh what it so just to come on that and
then
uh what what tags along with that
because you guys were talking about q
and on
is if the level of pattern recognition
that is creating
tribes is of such low bandwidth
isn't that a potential threat for
ai to capitalize on creating the
illusion of
of pattern inside some of these
conversations
and kind of kind of igniting and flaring
up tribes that's
not really coming from a human-centric
or human response
so i just have questions on that level i
hope that somehow they make sense
know it makes a lot of sense um
okay from a mcluhan perspective okay he
he said that uh in order for us to
survive
what we're going through right now we
may eventually need to uh
turn society into a technological
artifact
all right there's kind of a little
offhand comment that he made but it made
a lot of sense is that
that something that would actually
mediate
the conversation in a way that turns it
positive just like we you know
you know harness bureaucracies and we
put place rules for them
put in place rules for markets and how
that works but to do this on a network
scale you actually have to have
something that
can handle you know billions of
interactions and billions of people
and that can only be done through ai
and if you look at it from that
perspective a lot of what we're seeing
the battle
between the tribes is over who gets to
control
how that technological artifact is built
who gets to set what is trained against
what is trying to optimize and
it that that means it's kind of a battle
for the future right now
so if one tribe dominates and it can
then
dictate and force uh all the big
social networks and the technology
companies to come after that
into alignment and that they are
constantly seeking out
behaviors that they find objectionable
or an existential threat
uh whether it's other tribes on the
right or tribes on the left then it's
lock down time and and that we get
locked in
using this technology into a single
way of of thinking a single approach to
the world
and it's opaque and it's hidden and it's
not something that
you can you can avoid because it's baked
into all the technology platforms
and ai will be into you know every
single product that we touch
within the next 10 to 20 years every
single one
and it's in all the services that we
touch so that's kind of the great
lockdown that's what i call the lock the
long night
you know one of the mechanisms for the
long night is that once that locks down
and then once you see it propagated
across you know countries
is that you just get this narrower
orthodoxy that doesn't innovate
doesn't change uh or people keeping
their heads down
for fear of ever crossing into
into the territory that would eliminate
their jobs and eliminate their future
um i don't see how you get rid of that
at that point
because it's so pervasive and uh that's
like a civilization killer
it's end game so um
that asks you a question i mean it and
um
yeah i think i answered it yeah yeah so
it
makes me realize like there's a
persistent confusion
like we're all there's all this like war
on sense making
but
but you there's this there's a sense
that i'm hearing from you and
it's really a thought that i have is
that our persistent need to
make the whole ecology information
ecology makes sense
pushes us toward wanting this kind of
lockdown you're talking about
right and i think the challenge is so
because there are all these people
trying to like
figure out cracked enough make sense out
of this and i think what you're saying
is we have to
we have to uh shift our way of dealing
with
a much broader information ecology
where the dissenting and the noise is
part of the information ecology
and it's this other need this hangover
we have
now that we see all of it to want to
lock it down and make sense
is the danger and this is like what i've
been trying to say about all these other
war on sense making uh factions is
because
that whole impulse is in the direction
of the threat you're naming
right yeah and uh that a functional
system
using network decision making it's a
network social decision making system
has consensus and descent right it has
that you've got to have that descent in
order to make sure that the consensus
doesn't kill us
yeah and it works like the brain this is
why you can go in and see competing
competing uh uh intentions all the time
because some are a sub
threshold because if the intention you
have starts to be
not evolutionarily contextual anymore
then the
other one comes and so this is i think
a message that i you know i'm very happy
to hear
you know you know this needs to
be made because the same people that
you're talking to
are making this mistake right they just
wanted to be locked down in
their direction correct that's the whole
move
right that's that's the mistake
yep thank you hey you're welcome
cool uh michael underwood you had a few
questions um
feel free to pick which one uh that's
most alive right now for you
if you're gonna mute yourself michael
oh yeah i don't think i have a well
prepared enough question so i'll just
pass
um i'll just add that i think
the if you look at you reframe the
problem a bit
around truth and you have this consensus
in the mainstream media and then you
have the
insurgency in the net various tribes you
know you could consider
a popular streamer to be his own network
tribe and they can be co-opted and
directed wherever you want
but uh that's the mainstream media
versus these tribes and
it's the narrative is like a football
and directionally um i think they're
so like for example q anon some of his
predictions are directly more accurate
than cnn
and i just think that's interesting in
terms of we were told that
there was all this russia collusion
stuff but then it didn't
it didn't happen so i think that's kind
of the interesting thing is
there used to be three news agencies
that could really trick the population
now the population has more of a chance
to
since make on its own right
yeah that's uh in general a um
you know collapse of the existing
decision-making systems uh
jordan uh paul of my friend jordan uh
calls out the collapse of the blue
church kind of the liberal establishment
um that the ability to control messaging
through the the big media has been uh
eliminated has been undermined um
in in it you know a lot of it's been
self-inflicted i mean
the big um decision-making systems have
really
screwed up i mean particularly in the
united states more so than almost
everywhere else
um you know with response to 911
i mean going in invading iraq and using
wmds which was clearly a
misdirection a lie in order to do it and
then
saying you know it's always on the edge
of actually being solved i mean
17 years of saying that in afghanistan
18 years
next year will be better and then um
you know the idea that you know
unlimited trade with
china essentially the same government
that
had you know gone through the cultural
revolution and
fought us during the cold war uh would
reform them
and that it would be universally good
for all of us if if we just let it go
um when you know you had al gore in 2000
you know in front of congress saying you
know hey we should
get them into the wto and open things up
and then here we are a
totally unmanaged relationship and you
know china's accelerated
global warming even if you may not or
may or may not agree with that it's like
accelerated global warming by 20 to 30
years
through its uh pollution-heavy
uh industrial expansion
and exactly the opposite of what gore
was intending but it was
it shows that kind of screw up um and
that uh now we have a
peer competitor a technological peer
competitor that's that's becoming
increasingly tyrannical
i mean it's got a tyrant's got a guy who
says he's
president for life so um and they have a
lock that you know they're locking down
their society
and then you have the financial crisis
which i think really you know
really stuck got got this whole ball
moving is that you have a crisis that
cost about 22
23 trillion dollars in in economic
damage um
and if you dug into it and you've been
watching that at the time it was just
fraud as high as a mountain of fraud and
people selling direct to pension
funds i mean it was just everybody was
having their way with the system
and nobody
was held accountable for it none of the
no no none of the people who were
who brought this on us uh
were sent to jail from
i mean it was intentional
you know hiding of what had actually
gone on and
and burying it uh you know after the
fact and saying well you know we all
have
you know blood on our hands let's not
let's not look at this
and that caused the tea party and occupy
to go it kicked them off
and that brought open source to you know
movements into the united states
and those morphed over time and they've
become tribes
since then so uh you know it's the
dysfunction of that
you know that blue church that liberal
establishment of the existing decision
making systems
it's their inability to get things done
and done in an effective way
i mean even the current crovid crisis
you know with the fda
giving the cdc monopoly production
rights over the
the uh the testing and then they flubbed
it
and then the slow release of power to
the rest of the public health labs
to ramp up production and that put us
behind
by about a month and a half and that was
critical
i mean almost all the casualties the u.s
has suffered um
you know the high rates were all in
those early days because we didn't even
have a feedback loop
we didn't have any mechanism to you know
to screen people or respond
because there was no way of knowing who
was sick
300 tests a day in march one that's nuts
it's absolutely nuts but again
bureaucracy
and i can understand the thinking of you
know the fda to do that i mean it
was doing it because it was emphasizing
quality over quantity it wasn't
recognizing that the imminence of the
threat but
nonetheless again bureaucratic failure
bureaucratic decision making failure
and then the coverage afterwards by the
media is
they're not even focusing on what really
went wrong they're focused on other
issues
so um yeah i mean it's it's a decision
making
failure across the board
boy there's a lot of questions it seems
like i've been watching this chat go
go and go yeah there's a lot of juicy
questions um
brian keith you have a question about uh
religion
yes sir hello john the question is we
have
some religions that in the past were
very effective at
forcing people into certain ways of
thinking and not allowing people to
deviate
we've seen in some parts of the world
religions are still very good at this
the question is in the united states do
you think it is possible
for any mainstream religion outside
let's say uh mormonism that still has a
pretty good lock on people
to reassert itself as being the primary
source of truth in the network age
yeah um there are a lot of religious
aspects to
the tribalism we see um
there is you know
you could describe a lot of the the
tribalism on the left is is very
puritanical
uh and that is uh it fights
using a moral warfare very similar to
the way
uh religions fight um
and that that that's definitely playing
a part i mean that's
you know religion is to a large extent
you know a tribal decision-making system
um it's the guardian of the the kind of
moral infrastructure
kind of the ethical infrastructure the
key of you know
who we are um and that we're seeing that
subsumed by
tribes i mean you know that happened
with the printing press is that
i mean you know when martin luther
challenged the catholic church he wasn't
like
alone in that there have been plenty of
challenges doing the exactly the same
thing that he did
except that when he you know nailed his
theses of
on the uh on the door uh
of the cathedral that was ripped off and
then went out to printing presses and
a hundred copies came back and then the
pamphlets
and uh dissenting voices appeared
everywhere and
vernacular bibles appeared everywhere
and that
fragmented that universal church so you
know
there is a kind of a thing going on here
with with a network decision making
that's that's similar
um
yeah it's a it's it's interesting who
whoever takes up the
kind of moral warfare banner and we're
seeing that
uh in network tribalism
is kind of a replacement for uh
a lot of what the traditional religions
have done in terms of
you know creating an orthodoxy and
creating a view of the world that
coheres people
so i don't really have a full answer on
what happens to the traditional churches
i do see that mainstream protestantism
has been under
undergoing a you know
kind of universal collapse um and that
there are some churches that have been
relatively effective at retaining their
flocks but uh
we're going to see very soon how well
they can
move into the online world into the
network world and
if they can't it'll be tough
for them
brian do you have a follow-up question
yeah i was just wondering about the
catholic church as a microcosm of the
big question
where we see some people in the catholic
church like let's say if you read ann
barnhart
who is very traditionalist hardline
saying the current pope is not the real
pope
uh the real pope is still the previous
pope and very dogmatic
zealous uh and in promulgating a view
catholicism that is very specific
and very here's how we're going to
behave in the way we think of old tribes
and then you have most catholics that
are not like that
and it may be that in catholicism we can
see
the fight between the small we retain
the real truth fighting against
the modernization like where uh the pope
the current official pope is far more
liberal than catholics in the past
and so i'm curious john if you have any
opinion about what's happening in the
catholic church in particular
um in general
i think it's much harder to
maintain cohesion based on something
you're for
in this environment something you know
a shared ideology or a shared uh view of
the world and that applies to religion
because it's so easy to pick apart and
so easy
uh to snipe at and it caught is a source
of so much
disagreement and there's a reason all
the tribes don't
aren't uh held together by
a shared doctrine or a shared uh view of
the world
in sense of what they're for because uh
for instance say you're in favor of
justice well you can't
no one can agree on what justice
actually means somebody says this is a
good example and everybody else would
say wait wait that's not the example
this is the example this is a
networking kind of fragments that
but they can't agree on what they're
against um
so maybe that's the way out for the for
for traditional churches is to focus
less on what they're for more about what
they're against
and building up cohesion from there
tyler you had a question about the long
night i copied and pasted it below for
you
you can admit yourself and read it to
john
oh great thanks i was just scrolling up
to get it um so in regards to
potentially countering the long night um
would it be possible uh in principle to
build something that functions
as the inverse of the social credit
system uh
instead of centralized coercion and the
group think from above
like in china uh something that could
potentially be decentralized support for
individualism from below
i think that the first thing you got to
do is is
slow down the pressure to censor
everybody
that you know our current moves is you
know censor everybody who's
spouting nonsense or anything that they
disagree with
um i mean i don't think the dissent is
is the problem
can you build a system that protects
that descent that allows it to form
uh i think that really comes down to
um the degree of influence people have
over the
big social networking systems uh you
know facebook for instance and it's got
three and a half billion people
right so uh if you could influence how
they
uh
how they use a and try to keep it as
loose as possible
you raise the amount of chaos that's out
there but you
preserve that descends function
it's really a question of how do you
balance the two how do you balance that
consensus
and with that you know with that
appropriate amount of dissent
um too much in one direction
uh you end up more like russia and too
much in the other you end up more like
china
you know i i don't see those as as as
good outcomes
does that help or i don't know if you
know what that gets into this idea uh
that i've been working on is this
this whole um changing the way we
actually deal with data
and we deal with ourselves online and
that we need a mechanism
as powerful as private property was in
terms of transforming um
governments in the 1700s into something
that you know
became engines of prosperity and and
wealth creation and
we've lost that we don't have that when
it comes to the online environment
you know our personal data is owned by
companies it's owned by government it's
owned by everybody and
we're protected by this
fictive uh fig leaf called
privacy that's ill-defined and it varies
depending on who you
who's talking about it whereas you
should own your data
and that everything good starts with
that
that initial ownership
um any progress in that direction uh no
absolutely none but you know it's uh uh
you uh maybe you get a little bit of it
in some of the
stuff i saw in california but the thing
is it's still this privacy thing is
still getting in the way of every
every major development um
you know privacy is just it is it it's
like saying uh you know
in the 1700s you don't have to own
property it's just
everyone's just kind of the state is
just
renting it to you or it's a short-term
lease or
or uh you know it just wouldn't work
ownership was it was the key to
providing the mechanism to
to to creating what we have today
cool thanks so this will be the last
question uh cyr
davis you had a question on um
[Music]
john's uh i think
that informs his research i copy and
paste it below
yeah i mean you could just literally
read it as such it's not a complicated
question
but yeah i'm just curious there's a lot
of people doing you know social network
research
at santa fe institute and other places
so i'm curious uh
how much how much you've looked at their
work
um i've read it as it came along i mean
i've been i've been doing this since
wow 2001. so 2003 with my global gorilla
stuff so i was kind of pre-dating
most of the stuff we see now
so i've been reading it as it emerged
it's kind of weird
um you know i wrote my first uh social
networking
report when i was at forrester in 1996.
so i was going okay what's the big thing
after the initial internet
and i go social networking i called it
personal broadcast networks that
everyone would be broadcasting their
their content and people would
subscribe to each other and they would
create this massive network of
shared interaction and people were like
how do you build this and
a lot of questions on that and then it
took me to 2001 to find a company that
was actually building something like
that
it was a user land software we built the
radio user land that was like the first
blogging platform that had rss
we pumped we came up with the rss spec
and and
open sourced it and made it possible for
the world to kind of do that
got the new york times to sign on uh to
using
rss uh you know and they
started publishing their stories with
rss in it and then we started doing the
whole interconnection
uh thing in and then took off and it
became the template for
if you looked at the rss streams on
radio user land back in the day
it looked exactly like twitter in 2002
you know
and it so a lot of the early stuff i was
doing in writing
trying to convince people to that this
was actually
a useful thing maybe i did the wrong
thing but um
getting their heads around it is a lot
of the stuff that's driving my thinking
now
and i didn't have any real help
there wasn't really a lot out there you
know it's
i saw something and it and there wasn't
anything it's like in 2010 i was like
wait financial crisis hit we have to
figure out something
economically to do something and i tried
to do something
i called open source ventures it's kind
of like a software-based company
that would allocate rewards
as an annuity stream based on your
participation so
as you accumulated data and you would
get
points and if that data was used to
train ais or as part of an
ongoing service you'd get an annuity
stream so people would make
based on what i could calculate you know
hundreds of dollars per hour investing
over the life of the contract or the
life of the
the venture so it was like
it was before bitcoin took off and
bitcoin would have made a lot of that
possible and it was like i don't know um
i've read a lot of stuff uh from santa
fe and other other places
and i i appreciate all of it's awesome
i've read the stuff from uh
uh roone felt and aquila over rand and
i've
used to do the a lot of stuff and a lot
of good stuff came out in first monday
and the like
a lot of independent writers writing
about networking
but if you have any sources that are
really good that you would like to share
i'd be more than happy to read them i
mean i'm always open to anything that
comes along i
i don't have any specific source that i
found that was so enlightening that it
it dominates my thinking i think um
it's kind of formed organically as a
result of
a myriad of influences over time because
it's almost like you know i mean i did a
lot of stuff in the previous world but
when
the online world hit 95 and it was my
full-time job as an analyst
it changed my life it changed the way i
thought i'd go finally it's
an environment that wakes me up
that can actually keep me engaged
instead of this kind of horribly slow
and
target though you know offline world and
it's been that like
that way ever since so um
constantly bringing in new resources
constantly finding new stuff
digging into things letting my curiosity
take me where
where my nose my instincts bring me so
there you go that answer it or not
answer
um yeah i'd answer it thanks all right
thank you
cool so uh we're approaching the hour um
there was
a lot of questions we can get to a lot
of comments so i'll
send you the chat uh john you can have a
read at your leisure
um so there's anything you'd like to
leave us with to prep our minds for
for next week um well think of some good
questions we can kick in
because any any good question can kick
off a
you know 20 minute deep dive
we can go into the origins we can go
into fourth generation warfare and and
uh post-west family and nation states we
can go into uh
the mcluhan thinking in terms of
technology rewiring us uh the mechanisms
for tribes
you know how empathy works within the
online tribal structures
uh we can go into uh uh the collapse of
the balloon church
and um kind of the political elements
here and you know or
how they uh the red insurgency you know
took over the republican party
um and how the network tribes are taking
over the
uh democratic party now so um
yeah there's plenty of questions or we
could just talk futures you know where
things are going
and how things are how quickly things
can degenerate um
you know i have i put it like a little
blow by below in in the in the
long night report kind of a speculation
on one potential future
but that's not locked in stone it just
i under i just wanted to show the
dynamics in action
very cool right so um what's going to
happen now
i'm going to stop the formal portion i'm
going to stop the record we're going to
go a little break if you want to hang
out
afterwards you can leave you can leave
want to hang out we'll have like a sense
making session maybe we can figure out
what should be the next theme that we
can post for john if you'd like to
support
john or the stoa on patreon you can go
here um
yeah and thank you john and everyone
today thank you